we have already seen that a vliw
instruction really specifies several
operations Each of which operations
would have taken a normal instruction in
a normal super scalar processor the
instruction set for a VW processor
typically has all the normal Isa op
codes so each of the vliw instructions
can typically do whatever normal
instructions would have been able to do
in an outof order processor a typical V
processor will also have support for
full predication or at least very
extensive predication support this is
because it relies on the compiler to
expose parallelism one of the ways the
compiler does that is through scheduling
instructions so we really want the
compiler to be able to predicate and
thus expose more opportunities for
instruction scheduling a vliw Isa also
typically includes a lot of
architectural
registers the reason for this is that a
lot of the scheduling optimizations
require use of additional registers we
have already seen some examples of this
in the compiler support for ILP lesson
where we have seen that sometimes we
have to put some things in other
registers when we are rearranging
instructions so to help the compiler do
instruction scheduling we need more
registers than usual and we really
really want the compiler to do a good
job here so we will provide a lot of
registers to it another frequently seen
type of Isa support for compiler work
are the branch hints where the compiler
can specify to the hardware what it
thinks the branches will do this helps
the branch predictors and we also often
see some sort of compaction mechanism
for vliw instructions for example if we
have a four operation instruction and we
have something like this we do some
operation and then the next operation
needs to be here and thus we have to put
no Ops in here the actual V instruction
might include some sort of a stop bit
for every instruction in which case we
can put op one here then Mark this as a
stop and then we can put op two and op
three like this Mark this as a stop and
even squeeze in maybe something else
here so the idea is that instead of
having a lot of noops in our instruction
now the processor fetches this
instruction checks for the Stop bits and
in the first cycle does this in the
second cycle does up to the next stop
and so on so this helps a lot in
reducing the number of no and does the
code blow